Video games, which primarily target male audiences, have become increasingly popular over the past decade. One study reports that the sales of video games have exceeded those of movies. As video games have become more popular and more realistic, so has the need to assess the content and the impact of these images on their male audience. Martins and colleagues found that video game characters were significantly larger than the average male in America. Additionally, they reported that video games rated for children were more likely to contain hypermuscular characters compared to video games rated for adults. Harrison and Bond examined exposure to video gaming magazines, which are highly popular with preadolescent boys and showcase highly unrealistic muscular characters. They reported that boys in 2nd through 4th grade were more likely to desire a more muscular body after exposure to video gaming magazines. Collectively, the results of these studies are problematic, especially given the fact that children are less likely to decipher between reality and fantasy. Although gaming magazines portray cartoon characters rather than actual photos of males, young boys are likely to be influenced by the photos. Barlett and Howell found that college males who played a video game with an extremely muscular character for 15 min were more likely to express dissatisfaction with their own bodies. Preadolescent boys are highly likely to play video games; therefore, additional research involving young participants is essential.
Video game play affects the individual and culture in a multitude of facets. Evidence is presented to suggest there are many positive effects of video gaming on well-being and less evidence to support the ideology that video games lead to heightened levels of aggression in adolescents. We show how video games are affecting the dreams of gamers in our lab, allowing them to better deal with nightmares. The rise of active video games is spearheading the movement for health-based interventions in gaming, specifically those making use of augmented reality in order to encourage gamers to get off the couch and increase their levels of activity. We also demonstrate some ways in which video games are being used therapeutically. Research is presented to show that video games have been widely applied in education and training scenarios. We then shift our focus to the impact of video games on culture. We explore gaming culture itself and try to show how what was once a niche group of dedicated individuals has spilled out into a global phenomenon. We have also looked at the ramifications of gaming on important cultural issues like race and gender inequality, and social movements such as climate change. Lastly, we briefly discuss the up and coming world of eSports. In summary, video games are no longer a private activity relegated to a specific group of people. It is now a cultural phenomenon, which is literally changing our society. Video games have proven themselves as a dominant force in our world, and the future ahead is going to be wild ride, packed with new advancements and impactful change on our existence.
Media and video games in particular have become highly accessible and prevalent forms of entertainment. Research is beginning to surface that illustrates the impressive learning potential within video games. Moreover, the design principles present within many popular video games utilize a number of powerful tools for learning that have been elaborated upon by prominent learning theories. While recent research shows clear learning effects of video game play on a variety of cognitive and social skills, less work has been done on the potential that video games have to foster creativity among players. The current chapter discusses prominent learning theories that help explain learning derived from video games, provides examples of common game mechanics that engender learning, and provides a theoretical argument for the potential of video games to teach creativity. Special attention is also paid to “flow experiences” in video games and how such experiences may further improve learning.
The typical video game player is a male, between 25 and 30 years old, who plays between 6 and 8 h per week, and who has played video games for over 10 years. Video games are also highly popular among children aged 8–15 years, the majority of whom play between 30 and 60 min per day. Other player demographic profiles have recently emerged. In the last decade, the video game playing market has diversified following the introduction of casual puzzle games, mobile phone games, and online multiuser games that offer more socially driven playing experiences. These video games have attracted a significant female audience as well as players over the age of 35 years. The most diverse video game playing clientele is found in online multiuser video games, some of which attract millions of players. Males are at least twice as likely as females to play video games during adolescence, and males are more likely to maintain their video game playing into adulthood. Males also report playing video games for at least twice as long as females in an average playing session. Video game addicts in most countries tend to be single men in late adolescence or their early adulthood. Female video game addicts tend to be older than male addicts. Female addicts are also more likely to report a concurrent psychological problem, such as depression or anxiety. With regard to other technological addictions, females report greater engagement with non–video game-related Internet activity, including social networking and online shopping, and they are overrepresented in terms of pathological Internet behavior. The reasons for the lack of female participation in video games include the social stigma attached to female video game players, the hostile and overbearing online behavior of some males toward female players (i.e. females are not often socially rewarded for playing), and the masculine imagery and game-play mechanics in video games themselves (i.e. games are often designed by males for other males).

Cultural differences exist with regard to player preferences for video game activities. In Western countries, including the United States, United Kingdom, and Australia, fast-paced, first-person shooting games are a very popular choice among video game addicts. In Asian countries, like South Korea, Taiwan, and Japan, real-time strategy games tend to be more popular. Specific genres of video games, such as role-playing video games, also differ significantly between Western and Eastern contexts in order to appeal to distinct cultural tastes. The prevalence rates of video game addiction are also significantly higher in Far Eastern countries, such as South Korea and Japan.
Video games have become an integral part of American culture. Just as the invention of the television in the 1950s redefined entertainment and indirectly influenced many arenas of American life, the introduction of the video game in the 1970s has initiated a change in the nature of childhood play throughout society.

Where did video games come from? Who first had the idea to make television interactive, to give people the power to control the action on the screen? The origins can be found in one of the first video games, Pong. Video games actually stem from a very simple concept invented in the 1950s by an unsuspecting physicist working at Brookhaven National Laboratories in Upton, New York, Willy Higinbotham. Higinbotham's original ‘video game’ was designed to add some spice to a public tour of his instrumentation laboratory. Because Brookhaven was involved in nuclear research, these tours were organized to show visitors that the research was entirely peaceful and posed no risk to residents. Higinbotham knew that the tour of the facility was not very exciting, so he tooled around with an oscilloscope and a simple computer, built a few controls with buttons and knobs, and created what can be considered the first video game. The game was conceptually very similar to Pong: one player presses a button to launch a ball from the left side of the screen, adjusts a knob so the ball clears a barrier in the middle of the screen, and a second player hits the ball back over the ‘net’. With these modest beginnings, the video game industry was born.

Little did Higinbotham know that not only would his simple tennis game relieve boredom on the tour of his laboratory, but that players would form lines, eager to try their hand at the novel challenge. Before Higinbotham understood the potential of the demand he had created, marketers seized hold of the idea. In fact, Pong is simply a redefinition of Higinbotham's basic tennis game. The originators of Pong did not seriously revamp the design, but they did bring to it a new perspective. Realizing the game's potential for fascination (and remuneration), they grabbed their opportunity to latch onto the public's interest. As almost every American child can attest, their fascination has not waned, and the video game industry continues to profit (Flatow, 1992). Redefinitions are not limited, of course, to video games.

A split-second decision can also represent an attempt to redefine a field. Jeno Paulucci was a businessman who had just purchased Chun King, a canned food company. Paulucci wanted to use this company to sell his own food inventions, Cantonese vegetables with Italian spices. Paulucci had a meeting with the main buyer for a top food chain, and he was trying to sell his Chun King cans to be distributed by this chain. If the businessman was able to make the sale, his company would surely take off and become profitable; if not, it would be a difficult task to maintain financial solvency.

Demonstrating his product, Paulucci opened up a can of chop suey vegetables—and saw a cooked grasshopper sitting right in the middle of the can. Paulucci had one brief moment in which the grasshopper was hidden from the buyer by the open can lid. What could he do? If the buyer saw the grasshopper, the sale would surely not go through—and Chun King's reputation would likely suffer. Think about what you might do in such a situation.

In those few seconds, Paulucci redefined his role as salesman. Not only was Paulucci responsible for presenting his product to a potential buyer, but his chances of making a sale would be increased if he could convince the customer that he was a consumer himself. A typical businessman might have either tried to surreptitiously remove the grasshopper from the can (and run a high risk of being caught) or tried to explain the many legitimate reasons why the dead grasshopper was not indicative of his company's product. Paulucci decided to attempt neither of these two strategies. Instead, he looked the buyer in the eye and said that the vegetables looked so good that he wanted to have the first bite himself. Paulucci took a large forkful of vegetables—including the fateful grasshopper—and ate the large bite with a big smile. He got the sale (Hay 1988).
Playing video games has become a customary and important part of everyday life for today’s youth, and the broader education community has been exploring affordances of video games to support various competencies that are valuable for success in the twenty-first century. In this chapter, we discussed how video games can support creativity development both inside and outside of video games, and described our approach to assess creativity in PP. We based our discussions on the current literature, which views creativity as multidimensional and developmental.

To optimize affordances of video games for creativity development and assessment, there are several challenges that the community of creativity researchers need to address. First, we first need to rethink how we operationalize and validate assessment. As the creativity manifested around a game is considered to be specific to the domain (or the game), the conventional way of validating new assessments is by investigating correlations with existing measures, but that may not be the most reasonable method for creativity assessment in video games. Second, game, instructional, and assessment designers need to further investigate and establish particular design principles that are conducive to cultivating creativity.

Finally, well-designed games are challenging yet highly engaging. Such games often inspire players’ imaginations beyond the game, which provides opportunities to support all levels of creativity. Gamers actively seek out interesting and difficult problems, and strive for not just a solution, but the awesomest one. Thus we need to further explore ways to foster players’ creativity as an essential aspect of game play, which can lead to creative behaviors in other areas. We additionally propose that games can be used to assess different levels of creativity, and educators and game designers should consider assessment design methods such as stealth assessment and ECD to identify sources of evidence for creativity inside and outside of games.
Apart from video games being able to confer a number of benefits already described—those related to education, modeling prosocial behavior, alleviating pain, meeting basic needs, and facilitating social connection—there are some other noted advantages to playing video games. They can impart important skills, particularly where these involve fine motor skills or allow the player to simulate an activity. For example, studies have shown that laparoscopic surgeons who also play video games score higher for some aspects of laparoscopic technique. Other studies show that pilots who spend many hours on flying simulators tend to become better pilots. Overall, there are many professions where using relevant video games or simulators can increase professional skills.

There is also some evidence that playing action video games confers some cognitive and perceptual benefits. These include better selective attention and spatial cognition and faster processing speeds on some tasks (however it should be noted that there are also negative effects of playing these same games, such as poorer proactive executive control and overall attention deficits).